We're on the home stretch.
ホームストレッチに入った｡
This is the final step in the environment setup, and it's an easy one.
これは環境設定の最後のステップで､ 簡単なものだ｡
It's one that's easy to make mistakes as well.
ミスもしやすいものだ｡
But I'm going to guide you through it and there'll be no problems whatsoever.
でも､ 私が案内するから､ 何の問題もないよ｡
I'm going to show it to you both on a mac and a PC all in one video, so you guys can see how it works
マックとPCの両方を1つのビデオでお見せします｡
And it's pretty simple.
それはとてもシンプルなことだ｡
It's called creating a dot env file, which is a common way to store secrets in a way that you can access
これはドットenvファイルを作成すると呼ばれるもので､ ソースコード管理にチェックされることなく､
in your project that don't get checked into source code control doesn't go into into git, which means
プロジェクト内でアクセスできる方法で秘密を保存する一般的な方法です｡
We're going to start with a mac.
まずはマックから｡
Here I am, I am going to go into my projects folder that we set up into LM engineering.
ここで､ LMエンジニアリングに設定したプロジェクトフォルダーに入ってみる｡
So we are now in the project root directory, as I say.
というわけで､ 私たちは今､ プロジェクトのルート・ディレクトリにいる｡
Um, and what I'm going to do is create a file called dot env.
ええと､ これからやるのは､ dot envというファイルを作ることだ｡
And the way that you create a file from, from the, the way you bring up an editor in here is you can
そして､ ここからファイルを作成する方法は､ エディタを呼び出す方法である｡
And the name of our file, the thing we're going to create is going to be called dot EMV, literally
ファイル名は､ これから作成するものをdot EMVと呼び､ 文字通りピリオドを打つ｡
And then the letters EMV.
そしてEMVの文字｡
Now here's the thing.
さて､ ここからが問題だ｡
This is a fussy step.
これは気難しいステップだ｡
The name of the file must be exactly dot EMV.
ファイル名は正確にドットEMVでなければならない｡
It can't be like my keys dot EMV or EMV and it can't be dot EMV, dot text or anything like that.
私のキーのようにドットEMVやEMVにすることはできないし､ ドットEMVやドットテキストにすることもできない｡
It's got to be exactly dot EMV, otherwise it doesn't find it.
ドットEMVでなければ見つからない｡
So that's that's the rule.
それがルールなんだ｡
And now that I've done that, up comes a new empty file called dot EMV.
そうすると､ dot EMVという新しい空のファイルが出てくる｡
And what I'm going to put in here is very simple.
ここに書くことはとてもシンプルだ｡
And of course this is all laid out in the in the readme.
もちろん､ これらはすべてReadmeに記載されている｡
But I'm going to put in this file just open AI underscore API underscore key equals.
でも､ このファイルにはAIアンダースコアAPIのアンダースコア・キー・イコールを開くだけでいいんだ｡
And now I put in here the key itself that that I have hopefully stored very safely from the last video.
そして今､ 私はここに､ できれば前回のビデオから非常に安全に保管しておきたいキーそのものを入れた｡
And it begins scmproj dash blah blah blah.
そしてscmprojダッシュで始まる｡
Put that in the file and don't have any.
それをファイルに入れて､ 何も持っていない｡
Don't have a space before the equals sign or after the equals sign.
等号の前や後にスペースを入れないでください｡
And there's one other like really unpleasant.
そしてもうひとつ､ 本当に不愉快なことがある｡
Gotcha.
やった｡
If you've if you use the notebook on the notes application on Mac, I use that a lot.
マックのノートアプリケーションでノートブックを使っているなら､ 僕はそれをよく使うよ｡
Sometimes if you paste something in there and then press enter and copy it out, it replaces hyphens
そこに何かを貼り付けてからエンターキーを押してコピーすると､ 気をつけないとハイフンが長いダッシュに置き換わってしまうことがある｡
So just make sure that that whatever.
だから､ 何でもいいから確認してほしい｡
If you haven't copied it straight from that website, that nothing has got mangled in your key.
もし､ そのウェブサイトからそのままコピーしたのでなければ､ あなたのキーは何も壊れていないことになる｡
That was a really hard problem.
あれは本当に難しい問題だった｡
That it took me a while to track down that one student had, but maybe it's just a rare situation that
一人の生徒が持っていたことを突き止めるのに時間がかかったが､ そういうことが起こるのはまれな状況なのかもしれない｡
But anyways, if you've been careful, we've got the key just like this.
とにかく､ 気をつけていれば､ こんな感じで鍵は手に入る｡
You've got the full key laid out there, and then you press, as it says on the on the bottom of the
マックでは画面の下に書いてあるように､ コマンドOかコントロールOを押すと保存され､
screen on a mac, command O or control O to save, and X gets out of it.
Xはそこから抜けます｡
Now there's one thing to look out for.
今一つ気をつけなければならないことがある｡
If I do an LHS, you'll see that there isn't a EMV file here, and you'll also not see one when we look
LHSをしてみると､ ここにはEMVファイルがないことがわかる｡
And the reason is because any file that begins with a dot.
その理由は､ ドットで始まるファイルなら何でも良いからだ｡
A mac considers to be a hidden file, a secret file, and if you want to see that, you'd have to do
マックでは隠しファイル､ シークレットファイルとみなされ､ それを見たい場合は､
ls minus A, and then you see all of the hidden files, and you'll now see included.
lsマイナスAをして､ すべての隠しファイルを見ることになる｡
On the bottom left there is EMV.
左下にはEMVがある｡
And if I want to see what contents that has.
そして､ その中身を見たいと思ったら......｡
You'll see that it has the OpenAI API key.
OpenAIのAPIキーがあることがわかるだろう｡
And of course in your case hopefully you have a full key in there.
そしてもちろん､ あなたの場合､ そこにフルキーがあることを願っている｡
So that's it.
それで終わりだ｡
That's the Mac version.
それがマック版だ｡
Let's look on a PC.
PCで見てみよう｡
Let me flip over to my emulator of PCs over here.
ここでPCのエミュレーターに切り替えてみよう｡
Here we have it.
これだ｡
So on a PC the thing to use is the program called notepad.
だから､ PCで使うのはメモ帳というプログラムだ｡
And you can press the windows and R to run and then type notepad and press okay.
そしてwindowsとRを押して実行し､ notepadと入力してokを押す｡
And up comes notepad.
そしてメモ帳が登場する｡
Uh, in this notepad we say open AI underscore API underscore key equals.
このメモ帳では､ "open AI underscore API underscore key equals "と言うんだ｡
And then you paste in your key which should start scmproj dash blah blah blah blah blah.
そして､ scmproj dash blah blah blah blahを開始するキーを貼り付ける｡
That should go in here.
それはここに入れるべきだ｡
And then you go file and you go save as.
そしてファイルを開き､ 名前を付けて保存する｡
Now you then will have to navigate around to find your way to the LM engineering folder, which I've
次に､ LMエンジニアリング・フォルダを探すためにナビゲートする必要があります｡
And now.
そして今｡
There's like a little gotcha here, a little trick.
ちょっとしたトリックがあるんだ｡
You have to know where it says save as type.
どこに "save as type "と書いてあるのか知らなければならない｡
You have to change that to be all files.
すべてのファイルに変更する必要があります｡
And now in here you can type dot EMV.
そして､ ここでドットEMVと入力する｡
And I will save this right now.
そして､ 今すぐこれを保存する｡
And that should be done.
そして､ そうすべきだ｡
Exit.
出口だ｡
And now back over here.
そして今､ こっちに戻ってきた｡
If I do an LZ we do see that there is a dot EMV and it doesn't have any nasty name to it.
LZをしてみると､ ドットEMVがあることがわかる｡
So that has been created successfully and that is the final step.
これが最終ステップだ｡
We are now finally ready to actually go and do a lab.
これでようやく､ 実際にラボに行く準備が整った｡
Congratulations!
おめでとう！
I guess I should hold the congratulations until you see it working in the lab, but tentative.
ラボで動くのを見るまで､ お祝いの言葉は控えておくべきだと思うが､ 暫定的なものだ｡
Congratulations on getting it this far and I can't wait to see you for the next video.
ここまで来られたことを祝福し､ 次のビデオでお会いするのが待ち遠しいです｡
When we're actually going to do something.
私たちが実際に何かをするとき｡
See you there.
そこで会おう